

Computer Science Building, Office 254, 140 Governors Drive, Amherst, MA 01003, USA

Summary.

Ph.D. Candidate in Computer Science at the University of Massachusetts, Amherst. Advisor: Prof Peter J. Haas. Co-advisors: Prof Alexandra Meliou and Prof Azza Abouzied (NYU).

Ph.D. thesis on systems for scalable and easy prescriptive analytics. Thesis title: "Package Queries: Enabling Declarative and Scalable Prescriptive Analytics in Relational Data".

More than 8 years of experience in research, with several publications in top-tier conferences and journals in data and information management (SIGMOD, VLDB, CACM, VLDBJ). Multidisciplinary research, with publications in NLP, IR and robotics/Al conferences. Work recognized by several ACM awards (CACM, SIGMOD Highlights, invited VLDBJ, best demos and best paper at VLDB, best young research nominee in RANLP), and several scholarships (Krithi Ramamritham Computer Science Scholarship by UMass; merit, research and exchange scholarships by the University of Bologna).

More than 8 years of mentorship and advising experience. Mentored more than 20 students, at all levels (undergrad, master, and doctoral students), and managed several projects under my direct supervision.

Several industrial internships, both as researcher (MSR, IBM) and software developer (Cineca, Maggiore Hospital).

Research Interests

Research areas: Data Management, Prescriptive Analytics, Decision Making, Stochastic Constrained Optimization, Fair Machine Learning, Artificial Intelligence, Robotics, Natural Language Processing, Information Retrieval.

Research interests: Theoretical and systemic aspects of constrained optimization, decision making and prescriptive analytics at a very large scale; Structured, unstructured, and natural query languages; Scalable and approximate algorithms; Systems for interactive data exploration; Scalable systems for fair ML; Scalable systems for AI and robotics; Personalized text summarization.

Education

UMASS AMHERST Amherst, MA, USA Ph.D. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE 2013 - 2021

Bologna, Italy

Bologna, Italy

Jan - Jun 2013

Sep - Jun 2011

Amherst, MA, USA

2008 - 2011

2011 - 2013

· Advisor: Peter J. Haas

- Co-advisors: Alexandra Meliou and Azza Abouzied (NYU)
- Thesis: Package Queries: Enabling Declarative and Scalable Prescriptive Analytics in Relational Data

UNIVERSITY OF BOLOGNA

M.S. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

Summa cum laude

- · Thesis Advisor: Danilo Montesi
- Thesis: Temporal Information Retrieval

UNIVERSITY OF BOLOGNA

B.S. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

- · Summa cum laude
- Thesis Advisor: Danilo Montesi
- Thesis: Mobile systems for patient-reported outcomes

EXCHANGE PROGRAMS_

ÅRHUS UNIVERSITY Århus, Denmark

EXCHANGE PROGRAM DURING M.S., COMPUTER SCIENCE

· Advisor: Christian S. Jensen

UC RIVERSIDE Riverside, CA, USA

EXCHANGE PROGRAM DURING B.S., COMPUTER SCIENCE

Advisor: Vassilis J. Tsotras

Honors & Awards.

2020 Best Demo Award, VLDB 2020 Tokyo, Japan 2020 Best Demo Runner-up Award, VLDB 2020 Tokyo, Japan 2019 Krithi Ramamritham Computer Science Scholarship Amherst, MA, USA

2018 CACM Research Highlight Award (Invited journal paper in CACM Research Highlights)

MARCH 3, 2021 MATTEO BRUCATO

| 20 | OT1 | ACM SIGMOD Research Highlight Award (Invited Journal paper in SIGMOD Records) | Amnerst, MA, USA |
|----|-----|--|-------------------|
| 20 | 017 | Invited journal paper in the VLDB Journal, Special Issue on Best Papers of VLDB 2016 | Amherst, MA, USA |
| 20 | 016 | Best Papers of, VLDB 2016 | New Delhi, India |
| 20 | 013 | M.S. with Honors, University of Bologna | Bologna, Italy |
| 20 | 013 | Best Young Researcher Award Nominee, RANLP 2013 | Hissar, Bulgaria |
| 20 | 013 | Merit Scholarship, awarded to 0.2% of all students of the University of Bologna | Bologna, Italy |
| 20 | 012 | Research Scholarship, University of Bologna | Bologna, Italy |
| 20 | 012 | Merit Certificate, University of Bologna | Bologna, Italy |
| 20 | 012 | Complimentary AAAI Membership, Stanford Online AI Course | Stanford, CA, USA |
| 20 | 011 | B.S. with Honors, University of Bologna | Bologna, Italy |
| 20 | 011 | Merit Certificate, University of Bologna | Bologna, Italy |
| 20 | 010 | Merit Certificate, University of Bologna | Bologna, Italy |
| 20 | 010 | Exchange Scholarship, University of Bologna | Bologna, Italy |
| | | | |

Publications

1. N. Yadav, O. Youngquist, A. Fariha, M. Brucato, J. Killingback, P. J. Haas, A. Meliou Title hidden because paper uder review

ACL 2021 (under review)

2. S. B. Nashed, J. Svegliato, M. Brucato, C. Basich, R. Grupen, S. Zilberstein Solving Markov Decision Processes with Partial State Abstractions ICRA 2021 (to appear)

3. M. Brucato, M. Mannino, A. Abouzied, P. J. Haas, A. Meliou sPaQLTooLs: A Stochastic Package Query Interface for Scalable Constrained Optimization **VLDB 2020** (demonstration paper) pp.2881-2884

Rest Demo Award. Video: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1v5KevGKbfE

4. A. Fariha, **M. Brucato**, P. J. Haas, A. Meliou SuDocu: Summarizing Documents by Example

VLDB 2020 (demonstration paper) pp.2861-2864

Best Demo Runner-Up Award. Video: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZGzF6cBSYjo

5. M. Brucato, N. Yadav, A. Abouzied, P. J. Haas, A. Meliou Stochastic Package Queries in Probabilistic Databases **SIGMOD 2020** pp.269-283

6. **M. Brucato**, A. Abouzied, A. Meliou Scalable Computation of High-Order Optimization Queries

Communications of the ACM (CACM) 2019 pp.108-116

7. M. Brucato, A. Abouzied, A. Meliou

Package queries: Efficient and scalable computation of high-order constraints The VLDB Journal 2018 (Special Issue on Best Papers of VLDB 2016) pp.693-718

8. M. Brucato, A. Abouzied, A. Meliou

A Scalable Execution Engine for Package Queries

SIGMOD Record 2017 (ACM SIGMOD Research Highlight Award 2017) pp.24-31

9. M. Brucato, A. Abouzied, C. Blauvelt

Redistributing Funds across Charitable Crowdfunding Campaigns arXiv:1706.00070 2017

10. M. Brucato, J. F. Beltran, A. Abouzied, A. Meliou

Scalable Package Queries in Relational Database Systems

VLDB 2016 pp.576-587

Rest papers of VLDB 2016

RInvited journal paper in the VLDB Journal (Special Issue on Best Papers of VLDB 2016)

🔼 ACM SIGMOD Research Highlight Award (Invited journal paper in SIGMOD Records 2017)

R CACM Research Highlight Award (Invited journal paper in CACM Research Highlight 2018)

11. M. Brucato, A. Abouzied, and A. Meliou

Improving Package Recommendations through Query Relaxation

Data4U @ VLDB 2014 (workshop paper) pp.13-18

12. M. Brucato, R. Ramakrishna, A. Abouzied, A. Meliou

PackageBuilder: From Tuples to Packages

VLDB 2014 (demonstration paper) pp.1593-1596

13. K. Fernandes, M. Brucato, R. Ramakrishna, A. Abouzied, A. Meliou

PackageBuilder: Querying for packages of Tuples

SIGMOD 2014 (poster paper) pp.1613-1614

14. M. Brucato, D. Montesi

Metric Spaces for Temporal Information Retrieval

ECIR 2014 pp.385-397

15. M. Brucato, L. Derczynski, H. Llorens, K. Bontcheva, C. S. Jensen Recognising and Interpreting Named Temporal Expressions

RANLP 2013 pp.113-121

👭 Best Young Researcher Award Nominee

Professional Experience

INDUSTRY_

Microsoft Research Redmond, WA, USA

RESEARCH INTERN May - Aug 2017

Worked under the supervision of **Kaushik Chakrabarti** on natural language to SQL using neural networks.

IBM Watson T. J. Watson Research Center, Yorktown Heights, NY, USA

RESEARCH INTERN, WATSON HEALTH

Jun - Aug 2016

Worked under the supervision of Shilpa Mahatma and Yajuan Wang on "conceptual queries" for healthcare applications.

CINECA Casalecchio di Reno, Bologna, Italy SOFTWARE ENGINEERING INTERN Jun - Oct 2012

· Responsible for developing and managing a data warehouse and analytics system for a nationwide videoconferencing system.

· Duties included generating aggregated data and analytics, deployed through usable interfaces to let decision makers understand usage and performance of the videoconferencing system.

Maggiore Hospital Bologna, Italy

SOFTWARE DEVELOPER (VOLUNTEER)

2011 - 2013

- · Co-developed software to help the Emergency Room visit their patients using portable ultrasound technology.
- Software deployed on medical tablets to help doctors collect patient's information on the field.
- The collected data was then used to make better informed decisions in the Emergency Room.

DREAM Lab (Data systems Research for Exploration, Analytics, and Modeling), University of Mas-Amherst, MA, USA sachusetts

RESEARCH ASSISTANT Sep 2013 - present

- Working with Prof Peter J. Haas, Prof Alexandra Meliou, and Prof Azza Abouzied (NYU Abu Dhabi) to create 🏫 Package Builder, a system that extends query engines to support the generation of packages, i.e., collections of tuples with global properties that are true of the entire
- Technical paper at SIGMOD 2020
- Demo papers at VLDB 2020
- Invited journal paper at CACM Research Highlights 2019.
- Invited journal paper at the VLDB Journal 2018.
- Invited journal paper at SIGMOD Records 2017.
- Technical paper at VLDB 2016; workshop paper and demo paper at VLDB 2014; undergraduate research poster at SIGMOD 2014.
- Project website: packagebuilder.cs.umass.edu.
- DREAM Lab website: dbgroup.cs.umass.edu.
- Project code: Scalable-PaQL-Queries on GitHub

Design Technology Lab, NYU Abu Dhabi

Abu Dhabi, UAE Mar - May 2016

VISITING PH.D. CANDIDATE

Paper: Redistributing Funds across Charitable Crowdfunding Campaigns (arXiv:1706.00070).

AMPLab, UC Berkeley Berkeley, CA, USA

VISITING PH.D. STUDENT

Worked on extensions to Package Builder to identify ideal packages by example, under NYU Summer internship.

Data-Intensive Systems Lab, Arhus University

Århus, Denmark

May - Aug 2015

VISITING M.S. STUDENT

Jan - Jun 2013 • Worked on M.S. thesis on Temporal Information Retrieval under the supervision of Prof Christian S. Jensen.

- Actively collaborated with researchers within the group.
- Published two papers in main international conferences in the fields of NLP and IR.

Database Lab. UC Riverside

Riverside, CA, USA

Jan - Jun 2013

UNDERGRADUATE RESEARCH INTERN (VOLUNTEER)

- Worked closely with a Ph.D. candidate and **Prof Vassilis J. Tsotras** on query optimization techniques for query result diversification.
- Developed a query parser for a SQL-like diversification query language.
- Devised and developed a query optimizer to select optimal diversification query plans.
- Developed client/server technology to issue and evaluate diversification queries.

MARCH 3, 2021 MATTEO BRUCATO

Advising & Mentoring

Research Advisor for M.S. student Oscar Youngquist

Amherst, MA

UMASS AMHERST Oscar is working on enhanching SuDocu, our system for extractive document summarization by example. Oscar submitted a short paper to ACL.

Research Advisor for undergraduate student Agam Sandhu

Amherst, MA

Agam Sandhu is working on scalable stochastic constrained optimization under costly sampling methods.

Research Advisor for PhD student Ahmad Chatha (NYU)

Amherst, MA

UMASS AMHERST Ahmad Chatha is working on combining scalable constrained optimization methods with scenario-based methods for stochastic optimization.

Project Mentor (in collaboration with Microsoft)

Amherst, MA

UMASS AMHERST

Mentored MS students (Abdul Hannan Kanji, Parul Gupta, Ge Gao, Xinlu Liu) for their Independent Class project (CS 696DS), in collaboration with Microsoft, to improve the Fairlearn library (https://fairlearn.github.io).

Research Advisor for MS student Kanchi Masalia

Amherst, MA

UMASS AMHERST

Kanchi Masalia is working on SuDocu, a new system for personalized efficient document summarization by example. SuDocu website:

http://sudocu.cs.umass.edu.

Research Advisor for undergrad Genglin Liu

Amherst, MA

UMASS AMHERST

2020

Genglin Liu worked on the frontend of SuDocu, a new system for personalized efficient document summarization by example. SuDocu website: http://sudocu.cs.umass.edu.

Research Mentor for undergraduate student Kyaw Htet

Amherst, MA

Fall 2019

UMASS AMHERST

Kyaw worked on analyzing scenario reductions methods for stochastic optimization.

Project Mentor (in collaboration with Microsoft)

Amherst, MA Spring 2019

UMASS AMHERST

Mentored a group of four MS students (Katie House, Shanu Vashishtha, Deeksha Razdan, Cheng-Yin Eng) for their Independent Class project (CS 696DS), in collaboration with Microsoft to produce notebooks that showcase their Machine-as-a-service platform Azure ML.

Research Mentor for undergraduate student Nishad Ranade

Amherst, MA

UMASS AMHERST

Nishad worked on Monte Carlo scenario reductions methods.

2018-2019

Research Mentor for 1st-year PhD student Nishant Yadav

Amherst, MA

UMASS AMHERST

2018

Nishant and I worked together on stochastic package queries.

Research Mentor for graduate student Sandhya Sankaranarayanan

Amherst, MA

Fall 2015

Sandhya and I worked together on extending the package query language PaQL.

Research Mentor for undergraduate student Kevin Fernandez

Amherst, MA Spring 2014

Kevin and I worked together on evaluation techniques for package queries. This work was invited to present at the ACM SIGMOD 2014 Undergraduate Research Poster Competition.

Research Mentor for graduate student Rahul Ramakrishna

Amherst, MA

2013 - 2014

Rahul and I worked together on interface abstractions for package queries. Our work was demonstrated at VLDB 2014.

Teaching.

Teaching Assistant for Undergraduate Database Systems (CS 345)

Amherst, MA

UMASS AMHERST

Office hours, question answering, grading and labs. Teaching Assistant for Undegraduate Class "A Networked World" (INFO 203)

Amherst, MA

Fall 2020

UMASS AMHERST

Spring 2018

Homework grading.

MARCH 3, 2021 MATTEO BRUCATO Teaching Assistant for Undergraduate Introduction To Computation (CS 250) Amherst, MA **UMASS AMHERST** Fall 2017 Responsible for discussion sessions, occasional lectures, office hours, homework and discussion grading. **Teaching Assistant for Undergraduate Database Systems (CS 345)** Amherst, MA Fall 2015 Responsible for occasional lectures, project advising, office hours, homework and project grading. Professional Service & Leadership_ Reviewer • IEEE Transactions of Knowledge and Data Engineering (TKDE). **Guest Editorial Board** 2014 - 2015 • Information Processing and Management, special issue on Time and Information Retrieval, Elsevier, 2014/2015. **External Review Committee** 2013 - 2015 VLDB 2017 • SIGMOD 2015 VLDB 2015 RANLP 2013 **Lab Seminar Organizer** Amherst, MA, USA UMASS AMHERST DATABASE LAB 2014 - 2015 • Coordinated weekly discussion seminar, including invited talks and paper readings, for the UMass Amherst Database Research group (~10 Ph.D. students and faculty), and webmaster duties. **Student Seminar Leader** Amherst, MA, USA UMASS AMHERST DATABASE LAB Fall 2015 · Organized and coordinated a weekly discussion seminar among Ph.D. and M.S. students in the UMass Amherst Database Research group to foster research collaborations, exchange of ideas, group discussions, and group cohesion. Talks INDUSTRY_ Package Queries: Enabling Declarative and Scalable Prescriptive Analytics in Relational Data Virtually MEGAGON LABS Jan 2021 Scalable Package Queries in Relational Database Systems Redmond, WA, USA MICROSOFT RESEARCH Jun 2017 **Conceptual Queries for Multiple Data Sources** Austin, TX, USA **IBM WATSON** Aug 2016 **Package Queries: From Tuples to Packages** Berkeley, CA, USA BERKELEY LABS Jul 2015 ACADEMIA_ Package Queries: Enabling Declarative and Scalable Prescriptive Analytics in Relational Data Virtually HARVARD UNIVERSITY, DASLAB Jan 2021 Stochastic Package Queries For In-database Optimization Under Uncertainty Virtually at INFORMS 2020 **INFORMS 2020** Nov 2020 sPaQLTooLs: A Stochastic Package Query Interface for Scalable Constrained Optimization Tokyo, Japan (virtually) Sep 2020 • Video: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1v5KevGKbfE **Stochastic Package Queries in Probabilistic Databases** Portland, OR, USA (virtually) Jun 2020

• Video: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UrEOEplK06I

Package Queries: Enabling Declarative and Scalable Prescriptive Analytics in Relational Data

MIT CSAIL, DATA SYSTEMS GROUP Stochastic Package Queries for In-Database Constrained Optimization Under Uncertainty

MIT, NORTH EAST DATABASE DAY, SAMBERG CONFERENCE CENTER

Scalable Package Queries in Relational Database Systems

VI DR 2016

• Slides: packagebuilder.cs.umass.edu/papers/scalable-paql-presentation-share.pdf

Package Queries: From Tuples to Packages

AMPLAB, UC BERKELEY Jun 2015

MARCH 3, 2021 MATTEO BRUCATO

Cambridge, MA, USA

Feb 2020

Cambridge, MA, USA

Jan 2020

New Delhi, India

Sep 2016

Berkelev, CA, USA

Improving Package Recommendations through Query Relaxation

VLDB 2014

• Slides: packagebuilder.cs.umass.edu/papers/package-recomm-slides-web.pdf

Metric Spaces for Temporal Information Retrieval

ECIR 2014

Metric Spaces for Temporal Information Retrieval

University of Bologna

Metric Spaces for Temporal Information Retrieval

ÅRHUS UNIVERSITY

Hangzhou, China Sep 2014

Amsterdam, the Netherlands

Apr 2014

Bologna, Italy

Dec 2013

Århus, Denmark

Jan 2013